<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Delphi Foresight Strategy: Essays</title>
		<link>https://www.digital-orrery.com/essays/</link>
		<description>Essays about society, biology, technology, and the future.</description>
		<copyright>© Nathan Acks</copyright>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<atom:link href="https://github.com/necopinus/essays/raw/main/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 21:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 21:55:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>The Clarke Horizon, Part 1</title>
			<link>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2012-09-12The%20Clarke%20Horizon%2C%20Part%201.md</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Let us define the &quot;Clarke Horizon&quot; as the point at which technology can be considered to operate in an essentially magical fashion. By way of example and explanation, I'll use the sentence in which the term was coined: &quot;It isn't really proper to say that Dune takes place in a post-Singularity civilization, as the idea of the Singularity hadn't been proposed when the novel was written. However, it's fair to say that the setting is well past the Clarke Horizon.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not only is this potentially an interesting metaphor for the far future, but I think it gives us a potentially useful new way to conceptualize the Singularity itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let Δ be the time between the present, p, and the Clarke Horizon. Clearly Δ = Δ(p), though Δ(p) is not necessarily linear, or even monotone (though, of course, Δ ≥ 0). Now, consider a time T ≫ p. We can now say that the Singularity occurs if lim(p → T) Δ = 0 for some T &amp;lt; ∞.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a side note, our normal conception of &quot;progress&quot; probably boils down to the statement that lim(p → ∞) Δ = 0, while my own suspicion is that ∀ p, Δ ≫ 0.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 21:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2012-09-12The%20Clarke%20Horizon%2C%20Part%201.md</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Clarke Horizon, Part 2</title>
			<link>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2012-09-13The%20Clarke%20Horizon%2C%20Part%202.md</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, here's an attempt at bringing the conversation about the &quot;Clarke Horizon&quot; down to Earth a bit. I'm going to attempt to recap everything I've said previously in less technical language and annotate a few concepts along the way. The discussion so far has led to some revisions of the original concept; I'm not going to stop to explain what's changed - just take this post as the canonical &quot;state of the idea&quot; at this time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Science fiction author Arthur C. Clarke famously proposed in 1973 that &quot;any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic.&quot; Let's use this concept to define the &quot;Clarke Horizon&quot; - the point in the future where civilization operates in a manner that appears inexplicable - &quot;magical&quot; to an observer in the present. Most often this &quot;magic&quot; is technological (computers, for example, would be well beyond the Clarke Horizon of Roman civilization), but it may sometimes be social (for example, that modern cities can function as social entities at all would almost certainly be beyond the Clarke Horizon of our Neolithic forebears).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There's a couple of important things to note here before we move on. The first is that the Clarke Horizon isn't some fixed point in time - it's measured relative to the &quot;present,&quot; whenever that happens to be. As previously noted, our own civilization lives beyond the Clarke Horizon of most of our ancestors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the Clarke Horizon doesn't exist at a fixed &quot;distance&quot; from the present. During periods of rapid change the Clarke Horizon is much closer at hand than during periods of relative stagnation. Furthermore, the Clarke Horizon is more of a function of application than of general knowledge: Ubiquitous computing and augmented reality are rapidly moving us beyond the Clarke Horizon of those who lived in the late 19th Century, even though the principles that govern electricity and computation were well known by that time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The concept of the Clarke Horizon is closely related to two other concepts - that of the &quot;Singularity&quot; and the &quot;Seldon Crisis&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Singularity is a concept originally coined by mathematician Stanislaw Ulam in 1958 but popularized by science fiction author Vernor Vinge in the early 1990s. The Singularity represents the culmination of ever-accelerating technological progress, the point at which the rate of technological change becomes essentially infinite and all predictive efforts consequently break down. Since, at least at the present time, the distance between now and the current Clarke Horizon is primarily a function of technological change, we can redefine the Singularity in terms of this concept. To whit, the Singularity occurs when the time between the present and the Clarke Horizon shrinks to zero - in effect, civilization becomes magical &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt; for those of us actually living in it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, for the Singularity to really be &lt;em&gt;The Singularity&lt;/em&gt;, the distance between the present and the Clarke Horizon has to shrink to zero and then stay there. But suppose it doesn't. Suppose that civilization only becomes magical for a short time. Things will eventually return to &quot;normal&quot; - but what constitutes &quot;normal&quot; is likely to be vastly different after our brush with the Clarke Horizon than before it. And the longer we remain within the Clarke Horizon, the wackier things are likely to become. Such a case has certain similarities to that of a Seldon Crisis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The concept of a Seldon Crisis originated in Isaac Asimov's Foundation trilogy, published during the early 1950s. Originally Asimov conceived of a Seldon crisis as (per Wikipedia) &quot;a social and political situation that, to be successfully surmounted, would eventually leave only one possible, inevitable, course of action.&quot; Over time, however, the popular conception of a Seldon Crisis has come to be that of a great (but predictable) confluence of social and political events that will serve to rapidly and profoundly rearrange the structure of civilization in ways that are difficult to understand to those living before the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is this second definition that matches up with the situation where the present enters the Clarke Horizon for a short period of time, but then eventually exits. (This means, incidentally, that we can regard the Singularity as something akin to &quot;the Seldon Crisis that never ends.&quot;) Now, the whole point of the Foundation in Asimov's novels is to use the fictitious concept of &quot;psychohistory&quot; to navigate the Seldon Crises that occur to minimize the galactic dark ages that are the novels' setting. But if all bets are off once you've entered the Clarke Horizon, this would seem like a profoundly hopeless endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is where calculus comes to the rescue. Human civilization doesn't change that quickly most of the time, so it seems reasonable to assume that the function that describes the distance between the present and the Clarke Horizon is relatively &quot;smooth&quot; - and thus it makes sense to talk about the &quot;velocity,&quot; &quot;acceleration,&quot; etc. of the Clarke Horizon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;relative to the present time. These are what mathematicians call derivatives, and they give us information about how the Clarke Horizon is &quot;moving&quot; relative to the present. Moreover, we've already noted that the Clarke Horizon is a function of several different variables - not just time, but also technology, social conventions, and probably a host of others.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Civilization becomes &quot;magical&quot; once you enter the Clarke Horizon, which implies a discontinuity - a sudden change in value - for at least some of these variables. Derivatives are meaningless at discontinuities, but so long as not &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; variable experiences a discontinuity, it is still possible to get a sense of what range of trajectories civilization might be on after traversing a Seldon Crisis. We could therefore imagine something like Asimov's &quot;Foundation,&quot; whose job it is to identify approaching Seldon Crises and, once civilization has passed through, to quickly reestablish an acceptable trajectory by attempting to deduce the new values of the derivatives of the Clarke Horizon for those variables that suffered discontinuities during the Crisis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, this may sound profoundly creepy to you. And it should. Having some organization whose purpose it is to &quot;guide&quot; civilization is immensely problematic (guide for whom and to what end?), but it's worth considering one reason why we may want to invest in an institution like it: The Singularity. For the Singularity to really be &lt;em&gt;The Singularity&lt;/em&gt;, not only do all of the variables that define the Clarke Horizon have to suffer discontinuities, but they can never actually have anything but discontinuities &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; again. While some welcome such a &quot;Rapture of the Nerds,&quot; it seems highly doubtful that anything resembling civilization could survive such an event for very long. And that's the best case scenario (depending on who you talk to, the existence of the Earth itself may be put in jeopardy by such an event).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We all want to live in the great big beautiful tomorrow, but it's probably worth it to try getting there &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; traversing the Singularity. If we can come to understand the behavior of the Clarke Horizon well enough, it may be possible to choose trajectories for civilization that avoid Seldon Crises with lots of discontinuities, thereby minimizing the danger such events pose. A Foundation charged with this task might take as its Prime Directive (see, I can even work &quot;Star Trek&quot; into this!) that it should only seek to avoid the worst Crises, leaving as many trajectories of social and technological change as possible open at any one time. Perhaps it would be best to think of such an institution as something between an early warning system and a disaster preparedness agency whose purview is dislocations in civilization itself, rather than natural disasters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There's probably a whole new cross-disciplinary field of study here. Certainly we're talking about something a lot heavier and with a broader scope than economics, political science, or social psychology currently has. Perhaps we should just call it &quot;psychohistory&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/././2012-09-12The%20Clarke%20Horizon%2C%20Part%201.md&quot;&gt;The Clarke Horizon, Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 21:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2012-09-13The%20Clarke%20Horizon%2C%20Part%202.md</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Transparent Society</title>
			<link>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2013-10-06%20The%20Transparent%20Society.md</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;While I agree with the advocates off the &quot;Transparent Society&quot;, I don't think they appreciate for the most part how radical that transparency is going to have to be, or how fundamentally our society is going to have to change because of it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem here is not just that you can't put the surveillance genie back in the bottle, but that both the things that enable surveillance only get cheaper and more widely available with time. and that intentionally weak cryptographic systems can be exploited by everyone. If the surveillance state grows - even if we are able to extract equivalent levels of transparency and accountability - then eventually we're going to run into a situation where it's trivially east to spy on everyone, both because the technology is cheap and ubiquitous, and also because the systems that would act as a counterbalance will have been effectively neutered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm skeptical of the law's ability to constrain behavior at that point (law moves slowly enough that it already plays the role of court jester to increasingly dislocating technological innovations). This doesn't just mean that everyone's going to get 15 minutes of amateur porn-star fame. It means that it's going to be essentially impossible to guarantee the integrity of our communications - the emails you write, the phone calls you make, and the bank accounts you put your money into. All are secured by the same technologies, which means all are gong to become (practically) wide-open.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You might try to prevent that with massive, totalitarian-style surveillance, but that just creates a bigger, juicier target. I can envision people adapting to this by adopting radically open and accepting cultural norms (though I worry about the homogenizing nature of such global &quot;total information awareness,&quot; both due to outright coercion and the inescapable cacophony of the dominant culture), but I can't envision any economic system built around tallying up one's &quot;contributions&quot; (i.e., anything that involves any form of currency) surviving in a world where the records of such transactions are so totally vulnerable to being rewritten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That's a far weirder, more disturbing, and more perilous world than Dr. Brin &amp;amp; co. seem willing to consider.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.davidbrin.com/transparency.html&quot;&gt;David Brin's transparency page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 21:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2013-10-06%20The%20Transparent%20Society.md</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Unknown Knowns</title>
			<link>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2013-10-20%20Unknown%20Knowns.md</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;A lot of folks have made fun of Donald Rumsfeld's remarks in the lead up to the Iraq War.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are known knowns; there are things we know that we know.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are known unknowns; that is to say, there are things that we now know we don't know.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But there are also unknown unknowns; there are things we do not know we don't know.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Certainly, at the time, I was one of the folks who reacted with derision to Rumsfeld's remarks. But the older I've grown, the more I've actually come to like the classification of knowledge pertinent to the decision-making process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There's a nice symmetry to the classification system as well, with one glaring omission: What are &quot;unknown knowns&quot;?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Slavoj Žižek has proposed that &quot;unknown knowns&quot; are &quot;the disavowed beliefs, suppositions and obscene practices we pretend not to know about, even though they form the background of our public values.&quot; That's an interesting definition, and certainly a useful rhetorical device for the point Žižek was making at the time, but I find it lacking. In particular, it doesn't fit in with the narrative structure of the rest of Rumsfeld's quote, which would indicate that an &quot;unknown known&quot; is &quot;things we do not know that we know.&quot; The obvious interpretation of Žižek's statement is that &quot;there are things that (almost) everyone knows, but no one acknowledges,&quot; but this doesn't actually seem to be the equivalent of something that is known but not known (unless perhaps, one is a rock star philosopher with delusions of authoritarian grandeur), but rather just something you don't talk about in polite company (and perhaps, even, with yourself).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think a better take on the definition of an &quot;unknown known&quot; is &quot;that knowledge which we already possess, but which is not accessible in the decision-making process for reasons of either misunderstanding or ignorance.&quot; This is a take which, I think, is on firmer ground with respect to the process by which decisions - and, in fact, discoveries - are made. A brief survey of the history of science or engineering, for example, will reveal that many &quot;discoveries&quot; are in fact less about new ideas, and more about putting existing ideas which were previously regarded as separate together in context. (This is a theme that Harry Harrison explores extensively within &quot;The Hammer and The Cross&quot; trilogy, which is a really excellent read, even if it jumps the shark a bit in the final volume.) Alternately, &quot;known unknowns&quot; might be regarded as information known within some parts of an organization that is inaccessible to other parts because of political infighting, deference to authority, the fact that no one has ever thought to ask, etc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's worth noting that Žižek's more polemic definition &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be considered a special case of this one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In any event, I think this is a more useful way of conceptualizing the concept of an &quot;unknown known.&quot; It's certainly more useful in day-to-day life. I think it's also more interesting in the broader social context as well, since it suggests that the process of discovering &quot;unknown knowns&quot; may be a &quot;low-hanging fruit&quot; - and perhaps even one of the primary drivers - of social and technological progress.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The identification of &quot;unknown knowns&quot; with knowledge that exists but whose distribution is so poor as to make it largely inaccessible is also a strong argument for the preservation of human culture and thought. &quot;Unknown knowns&quot; are likely to be the type of human knowledge that is the most vulnerable to loss (becoming either &quot;unknown unknowns&quot; or, as is the case with so many historical mysteries, &quot;known unknowns&quot;), and whose loss we will likely feel the most acutely (even if we do not know why).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_Rumsfeld&quot;&gt;Donald Rumsfeld (Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/There_are_known_knowns&quot;&gt;There are known knowns (Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq_War&quot;&gt;Iraq War (Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slavoj_%C5%BDi%C5%BEek&quot;&gt;Slavoj Žižek&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lacan.com/zizekrumsfeld.htm&quot;&gt;What Rumsfeld Doesn't Know That He Knows About Abu Ghraib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://kohenari.net/post/22658005949/zizek-authoritarian&quot;&gt;Žižek the Authoritarian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hammer_and_the_Cross&quot;&gt;The Hammer and The Cross (Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jumping_the_shark&quot;&gt;Jumping the shark (Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 21:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2013-10-20%20Unknown%20Knowns.md</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Kobayashi Maru</title>
			<link>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2016-06-21%20The%20Kobayashi%20Maru.md</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;2016 is the Kobayashi Maru scenario of Western democracy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kobayashi_Maru&quot;&gt;Kobayashi Maru (Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 21:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2016-06-21%20The%20Kobayashi%20Maru.md</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Prime Directive</title>
			<link>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2016-06-22%20The%20Prime%20Directive.md</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Hyperbolic headlines aside, I'm not 100% sure that any other species has entered into a phase of development that we could recognize as a precursor to the emergence of complex (&quot;human-like&quot;) societies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But say that we did see this, and did recognize it… Should we have a Prime Directive when interacting with such an emerging non-human society? Should we hide our own existence from them? What happens if they come to suffer because of human-caused environmental degradation? What if they degrade their own local environment, but are unable to migrate because of the isolation we've imposed? What are our rights and obligations, both ethically and legally, to such a society? How does this change our conception of the non-human environment, and our rights and obligations to it?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And what if it turns out that there are in fact many such proto-societies, some of which exist in birds, or whales, or octopi, and it is impossible &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to interact with them?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sci-news.com/archaeology/macaques-thailand-stone-age-03944.html&quot;&gt;Wild Macaques in Thailand Have Entered Stone Age&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prime_Directive&quot;&gt;Prime Directive (Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 21:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2016-06-22%20The%20Prime%20Directive.md</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Te Urewera</title>
			<link>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2016-09-05%20Te%20Urewera.md</link>
			<description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; This short &quot;essay&quot; was written in response to a video a friend posted on my Facebook timeline about New Zealand granting the Te Urewera national park legal personhood - an idea that another (lawyer) friend took some exception to in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;So… Color me cautiously optimistic? But the devil's always in the details, and I'd need to understand the situation a lot better than the information in the video allows to really come down on this one way or another.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some background thinking…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've been going on for a while that I think (one of?) the key question(s) that we need to be asking right now as we work towards resolve the failures of modern democratic systems is: &quot;How do we incorporate the interests of people who are not people into our decision-making processes?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In other words, how do we recognize the interests of - and our responsibilities to - non-human, trans-human, and not-yet-human entities? A lot of things fall under this broad class of entities: Future (unborn) generations, human ethnic groups and communities, plants and animals, ecosystems. Some of these are humans (who are yet to be). Some of these are made up of humans (either wholly or partially). And some of these may not contain humans at all.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There's two motivations for this line of thought: (1) At an immediate level, human interests often depend on these entities in ways that we're unable to adequately capture at an individualized level, and (2) at a philosophical level, thinking about the issue in these terms is a way to recognize that our sphere of moral responsibility extends (far) beyond the purely human realm most of our conversations are restricted to.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The term &quot;people who are not people&quot; is a bit awkward, but I keep coming back to that phrasing because it captures the dual meaning the term &quot;person&quot; has come to have in our society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At one level, I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; think that we need to start thinking of these entities as &quot;people&quot; in a &lt;em&gt;legal&lt;/em&gt; sense. We already have a class of &quot;people who are not people&quot; in law - corporations - and while the system for dealing with those entities is flawed, it does provide us a framework for navigating our relationship with those entities (and their relationships with each other).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But this example also lets us get at the second sense of the word &quot;people&quot; - as a synonym for &quot;human being&quot;. And corporations (or communities, or animals, or ecosystems) are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; human beings. Again, however flawed it may be, we do manage to navigate this difference; we can talk about corporations have a &quot;right to free speech&quot; in one breath, but also acknowledge that they don't have a &quot;right to vote&quot; with the next.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Corporations are &quot;people&quot; in a legal sense, but that doesn't necessarily mean that we treat them as being &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the same as a human being.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, there's a key difference between corporations and the other entities I think we need to be considering: Corporations are made up of people who are contractually bound together within a clearly delineated legal scope. That's a big difference, so I think it's important not to push the analogy I'm making between corporations and, say, ecosystems too far. But I still think the example of corporations is useful, because it shows us that we can (more-or-less) successfully navigate these waters… At least with a simple, relatable non-human &quot;person&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, for the issue of Te Urewera's &quot;personhood&quot;…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If Te Urewera has been granted the status of legal person in exactly the same way that a corporation is a legal person (which the video makes it appear that it has), then I agree with Ryen Schimerman that this is immensly problematic. Firstly, Te Urewera is not made up of human beings, so there's already a set of rights that don't make any sense, and certainly one cannot talk about the park having &quot;responsibilities&quot;. But just as importantly is the fact that a &lt;em&gt;park&lt;/em&gt; is probably not a good candidate for consideration of the sorts of entities the interests of, and our responsibilities to, we're trying to capture here. A park is a human-demarcated piece of land, and I can't think of a single example where the boundaries of such an area match the ecological reality &quot;on the ground&quot; very well (or at all). The video seems to talk about Te Urewera as if it were an &lt;em&gt;ecosystem&lt;/em&gt;, but that almost assuredly extends well past the park boundaries. Moreover, the health of portion of the ecosystem within the park boundaries is almost certainly intimately tied to the health of the larger ecosystem its part of… Declaring the park a &quot;person&quot; is, in this sense, missing the forrest for the trees (or, if you will, the person for the arms and legs).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This also gets into some of the explicit concerns that Ryen Schimerman is bringing up, because when we start to think about Te Urewera the &lt;em&gt;ecosystem&lt;/em&gt; rather than Te Urewera the arbitrary boundaries, we realize that in this case we are talking about a gestalt entity that humans can be (though are not necessarily) part of. In this sense, once you have entered the park you have become part of the park, so the question of whether the park could be prosecuted for inhumanely treating an animal that died within it is a bit like asking how much responsibility you have to one of your fingers. Thinking about it as an ecosystem also lets us resolve the idea of trespass, which we again see is inapplicable because (1) ecosystems lack distinct boundaries they can trespass beyond, and (2) for the reasonscited above about ecosystems being gestalt entities, suing the park for trespass because a tree fell on your property is a bit like your nose suing your finger for picking at it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But all of these thoughts only make sense if we're talking about Te Urewera the ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think it's also useful to come back to the fact that entities like Te Urewera are made up of other entitites, whose interests may not always align. How do we think through these multiple layers of interests, rights, and responsibilities for actors both human and non-human? This is a great unanswered question; simply declaring a parcel of land a legal &quot;person&quot; neatly side-steps these issues, but the central problem with this approach is that it is precisely these issues that we need to be engaging with.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the face of it, I fear that declaring the Te Urewera national park a legal person thus simply papers over the problems we're trying to address here and, because of the arbitrary nature of the entity weve granted that status to (and its lack of good correspondence to the actual systems we're trying to address), we've created a whole set of potential side-problems of the sort Ryen Schimerman describes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Interestingly, the video mentions that the Whanganui River has been granted similar status. It's probably a much better candidate than the park itself, though again there's questions about whether we're talking about the &lt;em&gt;ecosystem&lt;/em&gt; or the geographic &lt;em&gt;feature&lt;/em&gt;, and how to deal with the diffuse interests of gestalt systems.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, that's a lot of concerns. I wouldn't say that I have the same visceral reaction that Ryen Schimerman does, but I'm likewise not convinced that this was as wise a move as it sounds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That said…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I do think we need to begin building the social, cultural, and legal frameworks necessary to bring &quot;people who are not people&quot; into our day-to-day decision-making process. I don't have good, pat answers about how to do this, and frankly I don't think anyone does. The way that we're going to figure out how to do this is by trying different approaches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some of these are going to be more incremental, like the lawsuit of &quot;Our Children's Trust&quot; on behalf of future generations that is currently winding its way through the US courts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some of these are going to be subtle, like the incorporation if the concept of the &quot;rights of nature&quot; into Ecuador's constitution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And some of these are going, frankly, to be blunt instruments, like the declaration of Te Urewera's legal personhood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mistakes are going to be made, ideas tried and then discarded. This is how we figure things out as a society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So while on the one hand I'm skeptical that granting legal personhood to Te Urewera national park will ultimately have the desired outcome (or even adequately addresses the issues it was intended to), on the other I welcome the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/theguardian/videos/557279487793152/&quot;&gt;Can a national park be a person? New Zealand says yes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ourchildrenstrust.org/us/federal-lawsuit&quot;&gt;Our Children's Trust: Youth v. Gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rights_of_Nature&quot;&gt;Rights of Nature (Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 21:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2016-09-05%20Te%20Urewera.md</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Challenge of a Post-Scarcity Transition</title>
			<link>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2016-10-08%20The%20Challenge%20of%20a%20Post-Scarcity%20Transition.md</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;A few years ago I had a part-time gig as a subcontractor at a major bank. Who I worked for was far more impressive than the large, sterile room I sat in. Most of the room was taken up by an enormous wooden crate that sat between my desk and the only door in. The sides of the crate and walls of the room were lined with low tables holding dozens of tape drives that the bank used to back up its computers every night.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every day at 9am I would come in and spend about half an hour swapping out the full backup tapes. Then I'd wait around for another four hours or so while my boss (who was based in Boulder and I hardly ever saw) remotely verified that everything was working. And then I would leave. I almost never saw another person.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One day I joked with my boss in the company instant messenger that I was really just a human robot arm. &quot;Well…&quot; My boss started to type back. There was an uncomfortably long pause.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;You kind of are.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That was the day I learned that the wooden crate that filled up most of the room was an automated backup system. You know, the kind you see in the movies where a robot arm switches out backup tapes, no humans necessary. The bank had purchased it some years ago, but then somebody did the math and realized that it was cheaper to pay some poor stiff minimum wage for 20 hours a week than it was to actually &lt;em&gt;unpack&lt;/em&gt; the damn thing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;The future is already here,&quot; William Gibson has often remarked, &quot;it's just not evenly distributed yet.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2efhrCxI4J0&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/necopinus/essays/raw/main/././Assets/Hackers%20Movie%20Clip%20Zero%20Cool%20(Dade)%20hacks%20into%20TV%20Station%20%282efhrCxI4J0%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hackers Movie Clip Zero Cool (Dade) hacks into TV Station (YouTube)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's easy to classify my time at the bank as one of David Graeber's &quot;bullshit jobs.&quot; At one level it certainly was. But I think it also highlights the fact that a post-scarcity world is only here right now for &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; people. For the rest of us, the uneven distribution of post-scarcity leads it to play somewhat contradictory roles in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, why the hell was I wasting my time swapping out backup tapes when I sat next to a machine designed to do just that? There were so many things that I'd rather have done with my life than sit alone, in a cold room filled with the annoying grinding of tape backups, for four hours every day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, that job was how I was keeping a roof over my head. I may not have loved it, but at the time my job prospects weren't great, and I needed the money. Every day I looked at that wooden box and was reminded that at any time I could be replaced. And what would I do then?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Navigating the transition between the present, where practical post-scarcity has become available to the powerful, to a future world where true post-scarcity is shared by all means navigating this contradiction. We would all be better off in such a post-scarcity future, but we're not all there yet. In the meantime, little has been done to address the immediate risks that such a transition poses to those who don't already live in that future. Why should most of us believe that a post-scarcity transition won't just be The Jackpot?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is, I think, one of the two great social potential barriers standing between us and a true post-scarcity future. It's also perhaps the easier barrier to overcome, because it's &quot;just&quot; a matter of strong social safety nets, regulation, and ensuring some minimal &quot;fairness&quot; when it comes to distributing resources. Oh, and making sure that we don't destroy the planet while we're figuring everything else out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is all standard political fair.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second potential barrier is more subtle: We judge our wellbeing relatively rather than absolutely. (This is obviously only true up to a point. A society where everyone experiences significant deprivation will focus primarily on just meeting its most basic needs. But the West has not been such a society for a long time, and the rest of the world is quickly catching up.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most cost-effective way to mitigate the first potential barrier is to focus on those who are least secure. But in doing so, our efforts will decrease the spread between the least secure and the rest of society, and consequently those who are more secure will begin to perceive themselves as less so (because they are now &quot;closer to the bottom&quot;), &lt;em&gt;even if their absolute level of security remains the same&lt;/em&gt;. While it's problematic to reduce any social movement to a single dimension, this is a useful lens through which to view the rise of far-right politics in Europe and Donald Trump's presidential campaign here in the US.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's less clear how to address this second barrier, but it does appear that culture significantly modifies the expression of similarly &quot;fundamental&quot; behaviors. Changing our cultural narratives around wealth and power may thus be critical if we are to successfully navigate the transition to a true post-scarcity society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/William_Gibson&quot;&gt;William Gibson (Wikiquote)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://strikemag.org/bullshit-jobs/&quot;&gt;On the Phenomenon of Bullshit Jobs: A Work Rant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://io9.gizmodo.com/william-gibson-on-the-apocalypse-america-and-the-peri-1656659382&quot;&gt;William Gibson On the Apocalypse, America, and The Peripheral's Ending&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Activation_energy&quot;&gt;Activation Energy (Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/news/the-point-of-no-return-climate-change-nightmares-are-already-here-20150805&quot;&gt;The Point of No Return: Climate Change Nightmares Are Already Here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/science/science-news/3315638/Relative-wealth-makes-you-happier.html&quot;&gt;Relative wealth 'makes you happier'&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/datablog/2015/jul/06/what-millennium-development-goals-achieved-mdgs&quot;&gt;What have the millennium development goals achieved?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.economist.com/blogs/graphicdetail/2016/05/daily-chart-18&quot;&gt;The rise of the far right in Europe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theamericanconservative.com/dreher/trump-us-politics-poor-whites/&quot;&gt;Trump: Tribune Of Poor White People&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://psmag.com/we-aren-t-the-world-535ec03f2d45&quot;&gt;We Aren't the World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 21:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2016-10-08%20The%20Challenge%20of%20a%20Post-Scarcity%20Transition.md</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A Hierarchy of Needs for Belief Systems</title>
			<link>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2018-01-07%20A%20Hierarchy%20of%20Needs%20for%20Belief%20Systems.md</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;A quick sketch of a Maslow-ish &quot;hierarchy of needs&quot; for belief systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is it functional?&lt;/strong&gt; Does this way of thinking help or hinder us in our interactions with the world? Belief systems that provide better &quot;results&quot; (creation of technology, feelings of well-being, etc.) can be thought of as &quot;better&quot; than belief systems that are not as functional. There is not necessarily a strict ordering here; functionality is contextual, and what may be more functional in one setting may be less so in another. In general, we can expect belief systems that provide more functionality on net to gradually become dominant within the noosphere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is it internally consistent?&lt;/strong&gt; Belief systems that are internally consistent can be thought of as &quot;better&quot; than those that are compartmentalized and non-aligned, in that they will be easier to teach to subsequent generations. They will also be more likely to fulfill higher levels of belief system &quot;need&quot;. In general, an internally consistent belief system will also be well-defined.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is it extensible?&lt;/strong&gt; Can the belief system be extended to &quot;think more interesting thoughts&quot;? An system of belief that allows for an infinite number of thoughts to be explored will be more interesting/pleasurable to think in than one which is finite. The most best understood extensible belief system is probably mathematics, courtesy of Gödel's incompleteness theorems. This is one reason why formal math can be so much fun.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Does it allow us to think interesting things?&lt;/strong&gt; This is more subjective, but belief systems that allow for more complex, &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; ideas will be more pleasurable/fun than belief systems that restrict our ideas. Belief systems that tie together more realms of experience (&quot;larger infinities&quot;) will be more interesting/pleasurable to think in than more limited belief systems. Formal mathematics has only tenuous direct connection to human experience, which is why most people don't find it very interesting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Does it allow us to think meaningful things?&lt;/strong&gt; This is the aesthetic level… Does the belief system appeal to our sense of truth, beauty, or ethics? I propose that meaningful thoughts are always interesting thoughts, but that not every interesting thought is meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that what is &quot;interesting&quot; and &quot;meaningful&quot; may very well change with time… What seemed profound to our ancestors often will appear to be quaint to later generations. Belief systems that cannot continually allow for the borders of &quot;interesting&quot; and &quot;meaningful&quot; to be expanded will lose their value over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maslow%27s_hierarchy_of_needs&quot;&gt;Maslow's hierarchy of needs (Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noosphere&quot;&gt;Noosphere (Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%B6del%27s_incompleteness_theorems&quot;&gt;Gödel's incompleteness theorems (Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 21:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2018-01-07%20A%20Hierarchy%20of%20Needs%20for%20Belief%20Systems.md</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Kobayashi Maru (Redux)</title>
			<link>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2018-06-23%20The%20Kobayashi%20Maru%20%28Redux%29.md</link>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Two years ago I wrote that:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;2016 is the Kobayashi Maru scenario of Western democracy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I still stand by this statement, though today I might say instead:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first decades of the 21st Century are the Kobayashi Maru scenario of Western democracy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think that many more people might agree with me now. After all, there's a lot of talk these days about how we're all well and truly fucked, from our economies to our environment to our politics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But in all this acknowledgment of the fucked-ness of our collective future, I do think that we tend to forget one thing…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most important part of the Kobayashi Maru scenario is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; that it is impossible to win. It is that, in facing the impossibility of winning, we reveal the true content of our character.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/././2016-06-21%20The%20Kobayashi%20Maru.md&quot;&gt;The Kobayashi Maru (2016 Essay)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kobayashi_Maru&quot;&gt;Kobayashi Maru (Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 21:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid>https://github.com/necopinus/essays/blob/main/./2018-06-23%20The%20Kobayashi%20Maru%20%28Redux%29.md</guid>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
